Register of the Poland. Poselstwo (Romania) Telegrams
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Poselstwo (Romania) telegrams,
1919-1939
59030
Poland. Poselstwo (Romania)
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Logbook transcripts of telegrams sent and received, relating to Polish-Romanian relations during the interwar period. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/49/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (3 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/49/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Historical Note
Polish legation in Romania.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains telegrams sent and received by the Polish legation in Romania between 1919 and 1939, as well as some correspondence between the legation and the Polish consulate in Chisinau. It is one of the best-preserved collections of its kind, documenting not only Polish-Romanian relations and the role Romania played as Poland's economic and strategic partner, but also Polish interwar foreign policy toward the Balkans, Italy, Central Europe (Germany and Czechoslovakia in particular), and the Soviet Union. Exchanged at the highest diplomatic level, the telegrams illustrate daily developments in the international tensions that culminated in the outbreak of World War II.
These telegrams were formerly part of the Polish Foreign Ministry collection, acquired by the Hoover Archives in 1959, and were accessioned in the early 1990s as a separate collection.
A microfilm copy of these materials has been deposited in the State Archives of Poland in Warsaw.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Romania--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland.; Romania.; Poland--Foreign relations--Romania.
Series Description
- Coded Telegrams, 1919-1939. (Box 1-3)
  Logbooks of incoming and outgoing telegrams
- Internal Correspondence. Telegrams between the legation and the Polish consulate in Chisinau, 1936 April 6 - 1939 September 18 (Box 3)
Container List
- CODED TELEGRAMS, 1919-1939. (Box 1)
  Logbooks
  - General - "Ksiega szyfrow"
    - Nr. 1, 1919 June 17 - 1925 September 27 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Nr. 2, 1925 October 1 - 1928 May 8 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Nr. 3, 1928 May - 1929 September 16 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Nr. 4, 1929 September 10 - 1931 March 9 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Nr. 5, 1931 March 9 - 1931 December 31 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Nr. 6, 1932 January 1 - 1933 December 31 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Nr. 7, 1934 January 2 - 1938 March 18 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Nr. 8, 1938 March 19 - 1939 September 22 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Nr. 9, 1939 September 22 - November 14 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Ambassador
    - "Ksiazka szyfrow osobistych i sekretowanych," 1936 October 5 - 1939 November 10 (Folder 3: 4)
    - "Telegramy osobiste Pana Posla: Ksiazka Nr. 1," 1931-1933 (Folder 3: 5)
- INTERNAL CORRESPONDENCE. Telegrams between the legation and the Polish consulate in Chisinau (Kiszyniow), 1936 April 6 - 1939 September 18 (Folder 3: 6)